Guide to the Society of Iconophiles Print Collection 1895-1929 PR 160
New-York Historical Society
Society of Iconophiles Print Collection
1895-1929
New-York Historical Society
PR 160
2 Linear feet (4 boxes, 1 drawer)
Collection of prints, mostly New York scenes, issued by the Society of Iconophiles.
Provenance
Some prints were purchased as they were issued. Others are from a variety of donors. Many prints were given to the Society as part of the Hall Park McCullough estate gift, 1971.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
The Society of Iconophiles was formed in 1894 by William Loring Andrews (1837-1920), a member of the Grolier Club. Its stated purpose was to issue series of engraved views of New York City and portraits of prominent persons connected with New York City. Each series of engravings was issued in an edition of 101. Eleven of these were proofs before letter, which were signed by the engraver. The plates were destroyed after this first printing. The Society initially limited itself to ten members, each of whom was to receive one of these signed proofs. The other 90 prints were sold to the public. In 1905, the Society of Iconophiles enlarged its circle by creating fifty Associate Members, who subscribed to the upcoming print series. The initial group of ten became known as the Active Members. During its tenure, the Society produced seventeen discrete series of prints, other assorted prints, and several volumes. The Society of Iconophiles ceased to exist in 1939.
Scope and Content Note
The Society of Iconophiles Print Collection spans the period from 1895 to 1929 and contains an almost complete set of the prints issued by the Society during its existence. Many duplicate prints and some explanatory material are included. The collection includes engravings (including aquatint and mezzotint), etchings, lithographs, and photogravures. The collection is divided into sixteen series after the Society's published print series: Twelve Engravings by Edwin D. French; Twelve Lithographs by C. F. W. Mielatz; Six Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King; Six Portraits, with Views, Engraved by Francis S. King; Ten Facsimiles of Early Engraved Views Reengraved by Sidney L. Smith; Two Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King; Eight Aquatints by C.F.W. Mielatz; Twelve Lithographs by Joseph Pennell; Twelve Engravings by W. M. Aikman, Frances S. King, and Sidney L. Smith; Picturesque New York: Twelve Photogravures from Monotypes by C. F. W. Mielatz; Six Etchings, from Photographs, by Sidney L. Smith; One Mezzotint by S. Arlent Edwards; Three Engravings of Statues by Francis S. King; Six Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith; Eight Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith; and Two Engravings Printed in Colors by Charles Furth.
The subjects shown in the prints follow the Society's stated purpose: all are views of New York City or portraits of New Yorkers. Early views of New York, either reengravings or prints after oil paintings, abound. These generally show important early New York landmarks or buildings, such as the Morris-Jumel House, City Hall, Fraunces Tavern, the Tontine Coffee House, St. Paul's Chapel and other churches, and the Battery. Waterfront scenes and buildings, as well as views of the cityscape from Brooklyn and New Jersey, are common. Contemporary scenes of New York show some of these same buildings, as well as those more recently built. Views of lower Manhattan prevail, although a few early twentieth century views show Union Square, Times Square, and several points in between.
Portraits include early American engravers, such as Alexander Anderson and Paul Revere; politicians and military leaders like DeWitt Clinton, George Washington, William Tecumseh Sherman, and General Lafayette; and poets Fitz-Greene Halleck and Joseph Rodman Drake.
Artists commissioned by the Society of Iconophiles were Edwin Davis French and Sidney L. Smith, bookplate artists who were favorites of the Grolier Club members; printmakers Francis Scott King, Charles Frederick William Mielatz, and Walter M. Aikman; and the celebrated lithographer and illustrator Joseph Pennell.
Series titles were taken from A List of Engravings Issued by the Society of Iconophiles, 1895-1925. This and several other catalogs can be found in the front of Box 1. Prospectus about the launch of a new series or a specific print from a series are filed at the end of each series' prints. Print titles and dates were transcribed from the letterpress-printed wrappers issued to hold each set of prints.
Some series contain prints made from cancelled plates or proofs from the series; as described above, these proofs were issued only to the ten Active Members of the Society. Almost all prints are enclosed in individual folders or are foldered together by series. Provenance information is generally listed in pencil on the verso or the bottom right corner of each print. Prints are listed individually in the box listing, with notation as to the number of copies held; no notation indicates one copy. Several prints from a few series were lacking at the time of cataloging; these prints may not have ever been held by the New-York Historical Society, but are listed in brackets in the box listing in order to show a complete series list.
Arrangement
Organized in sixteen series, after the series of prints published by the Society of Iconophiles.
Missing Title
Series I. Twelve Engravings by Edwin D. French
Series II. Twelve Lithographs by C. F. W. Mielatz
Series III. Six Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King
Series IV. Six Portraits, with Views, Engraved by Francis S. King
Series V. Ten Facsimiles of Early Engraved Views Reengraved by Sidney L. Smith
Series VI. Two Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King
Series VII. Eight Aquatints by C.F.W. Mielatz
Series VIII. Twelve Lithographs by Joseph Pennell
Series IX. Twelve Engravings by W. M. Aikman, Frances S. King, and Sidney L. Smith
Series X. Picturesque New York: Twelve Photogravures from Monotypes by C. F. W. Mielatz
Series XI. Six Etchings, from Photographs, by Sidney L. Smith
Series XII. One Mezzotint by S. Arlent Edwards
Series XIII. Three Engravings of Statues by Francis S. King
Series XIV. Six Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith
Series XV. Eight Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith
Series XVI. Two Engravings Printed in Colors by Charles Furth
Separated Material
Catalogue of the Engravings issued by the Society of Iconophiles of the City of New York (1908) is in the New-York Historical Society's Library.
Portraits.; Photogravures; Mezzotints (prints); Lithographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Etchings (prints); Engravings (prints); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Aquatints (prints); Streets -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.
- Series I: Twelve Engravings by Edwin D. French
  - 1. St. Paul's Chapel (2 copies), 1895 Feb. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2. The Chancel of St. Paul's Chapel (3 copies), 1895 Apr. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - 3. Fraunces' Tavern (2 copies), 1895 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - 4. The Roger Morris House, 1895 Jun. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - 5. The Hamilton Grange (3 copies), 1895 Dec. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - 6. St. Mark's Church (3 copies), 1896 Feb. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - 7. The City Hall (2 copies), 1896 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - 8. The Halls of Justice ("The Tombs") (3 copies), 1896 Sep. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - 9. National Academy of Design (3 copies), 1896 Nov. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - 10. St. John's Chapel, Varick Street (2 copies), 1896 Dec. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - 11. The Murray Hill Distributing Reservoir (3 copies), 1897 Jan. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - 12. The Bowling Green (3 copies), 1897 Mar. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Twelve Lithographs by C. F. W. Mielatz
  - 1. The Battery and Castle Garden, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2. Morningside Park and St. Luke's Hospital, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 3. The Aaron Burr House, No. 11 Reade Street, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 4. Clinton Hall from a sketch made in 1889, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 5. High Bridge, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 6. On the Harlem River, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - 7. South Street from Coenties' Slip, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 8. Oyster Market, near Christopher Street, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 9. Dutch Reformed Church, Kingsbridge Road, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 10. "Five Points", 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 11. The Poe Cottage, Fordham, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - 12. Old Mill, Van Cortlandt Park, 1899 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Series III: Six Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King
  - 1. [Hugh Gaine] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 2. Isaiah Thomas, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 3. Paul Revere, 1899 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 4. Alexander Anderson, 1899 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 5. James Rivington, 1901 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - 6. Amos Doolittle, 1901 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Six Portraits, with Views, Engraved by Francis S. King
  Scope and Contents note
  Each portrait is foldered with an accompanying text.
  - 1. Portrait of General Lafayette and a view of his Landing in New York in 1824 (2 copies), 1899 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - 2. Portrait of Washington and a view of the Evacuation of New York by the British November 25, 1783 (3 copies), 1899 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - 3. Portrait of DeWitt Clinton and a view of the Battery and Water Parade at the Celebration of the Opening of the Erie Canal November 4th, 1825 (3 copies), 1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - 4. Portrait of Admiral Dewey Commemorating his Arrival in New York September 1899 (3 copies), 1902 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  - 5. Portrait of Aaron Burr and a view of "Richmond Hill"(3 copies), 1902 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - 6. Portrait of Alexander Hamilton and a view of "The Grange" (2 copies), 1902 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Ten Facsimiles of Early Engraved Views Reengraved by Sidney L. Smith
  - 1. Federal Hall (3 copies), 1899 Oct. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - 2. New or Middle Dutch Church (5 copies), 1900 Mar. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
  - 3. Columbia College (3 copies), 1900 Jun. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - 4. Trinity Church (3 copies), 1900 Oct. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
  - 5. Richmond Hill House (4 copies), 1901 Mar. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
  - 6. St. Paul's Chapel (3 copies), 1901 May (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - 7. Government House (4 copies), 1902 Jan. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
  - 8. City (Federal) Hall, Wall Street (3 copies), 1902 Mar. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - 9. Belvedere House (3 copies), 1903 Jan. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
  - 10. The Battery and Harbor (3 copies), 1903 Mar. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
- Series VI: Two Portraits Engraved by Francis S. King
  - 1. Portrait of Fitz-Greene Halleck (2 copies), 1903 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
  - 2. Portrait of Joseph Rodman Drake (3 copies), 1903 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
- Series VII: Eight Aquatints by C.F.W. Mielatz
  - 1. A View of New York from Fulton Street, Brooklyn (4 copies), 1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - 2. The Battery, New York, Esplanade and Castle Garden (3 copies), 1904 Jul. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
  - 3. New York Alms House now Bellevue Hospital (4 copies), 1905 Jan. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
  - 4. City Hotel, Broadway between Thames and Cedar Streets (4 copies), 1905 Jun. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
  - 5. Castle Williams from the Battery (2 copies), 1905 Sep. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
  - 6. Brooklyn Ferry, Fulton Street, New York (3 copies), 1905 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
  - 7. St. Paul's Chapel and the Rutherford House (4 copies), 1905 Dec. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
  - 8. Castle Clinton and the Battery (4 copies), 1906 May (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
- Series VIII: Twelve Lithographs by Joseph Pennell
  All prints are oversize and are housed in a horizontal folder in a map case.
  - 1. Battery Park, [1905] (Box Unknown container 460 for instance of 1. Battery Park, Folder unknown container)
  - 2. Broadway from Bowling Green, [1905] (Box Unknown container 461 for instance of 2. Broadway from Bowling Green, Folder unknown container)
  - 3. "Broadway Towers", [1905] (Box Unknown container 462 for instance of 3. "Broadway Towers", Folder unknown container)
  - 4. The Stock Exchange, [1905] (Box Unknown container 463 for instance of 4. The Stock Exchange, Folder unknown container)
  - 5. Nassau Street, [1905] (Box Unknown container 464 for instance of 5. Nassau Street, Folder unknown container)
  - 6. Pine Street, [1905] (Box Unknown container 465 for instance of 6. Pine Street, Folder unknown container)
  - 7. William Street, [1905] (Box Unknown container 466 for instance of 7. William Street, Folder unknown container)
  - 8. "Building the Building", [1905] (Box Unknown container 467 for instance of 8. "Building the Building", Folder unknown container)
  - 9. "The Flat Iron", [1905] (Box Unknown container 468 for instance of 9. "The Flat Iron", Folder unknown container)
  - 10. Union Square, [1905] (Box Unknown container 469 for instance of 10. Union Square, Folder unknown container)
  - 11. Broadway above 23rd Street, [1905] (Box Unknown container 470 for instance of 11. Broadway above 23rd Street, Folder unknown container)
  - 12. The Times Building, [1905] (Box Unknown container 471 for instance of 12. The Times Building, Folder unknown container)
- Series IX: Twelve Engravings by W. M. Aikman, Frances S. King, and Sidney L. Smith
  - 1. A South East Prospect of the City of New York (3 copies), 1906 Feb. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
  - 2. Broadway looking North at Grand Street (2 copies), 1906 Feb. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
  - 3. Clinton Hall, Nassau and Beekman Streets (2 copies), 1906 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
  - 4. The Custom House, New York 1799-1815 (2 copies), 1906 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
  - 5. A South West Prospect of the City of New York (2 copies), 1906 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
  - 6. New Amsterdam About 1650 (2 copies), 1906 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
  - 7. Columbia College 1784-1857 (2 copies), 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
  - 8. State Street, Nos. 16-19, About 1864, 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
  - 9. New York in 1775 from the Atlantic Neptune (2 copies), 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
  - 10. Broadway and Grand Street from an Oil Painting dated 1830 (2 copies), 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
  - 11. Grace and Trinity Churches from a Painting by Wm. Strickland (2 copies), 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
  - 12. St. Paul's Chapel about 1812 from a Painting by Wm. Strickland, 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
- Series X: Picturesque New York: Twelve Photogravures from Monotypes by C. F. W. Mielatz
  - 1. Van Cortlandt Manor House, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 2. Oyster Market, West Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 3. St. John's Chapel, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 4. Fraunces' Tavern, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 5. Old Houses on Battery Park, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 6. Rose Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 7. Old House, Broadway at Great Jones Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 8. Doorway, Third Avenue and 122d Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 9. Jumel Mansion, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 10. Coenties Slip in 1891, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 11. Rogers' House, No. 7 State Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - 12. Peter Cooper's House, Fourth Avenue and 28th Street, 1908 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
- Series XI: Six Etchings, from Photographs, by Sidney L. Smith
  - 1. Broadway in 1865, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - 2. Astor House, Broadway, 1867, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - 3. [New York Hotel, Broadway, 1867] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - 4. Bowling Green and State Street, 1880, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - 5. Wall Street in 1883, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - 6. [North Dutch Church] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - Announcement about launch of series, 1908 Jan. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
- Series XII: One Mezzotint by S. Arlent Edwards
  - 1. Alexander Hamilton, 1909 (Box Unknown container 472 for instance of 1. Alexander Hamilton, Folder unknown container)
- Series XIII: Three Engravings of Statues by Francis S. King
  - 1. David Glasgow Farragut, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
  - 2. William Tecumseh Sherman, 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
  - 3. George Washington, 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
- Series XIV: Six Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith
  - 1. The Tontine Coffee House, Wall & Water Streets, about 1797 (3 copies), 1910 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
  - View of the City of New York from Mount Pitt, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
  - 3. View of the City of New York from Long Island [St. Memin View] (3 copies), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 43)
  - 4. A View of the City of New York from Long Island [Montresor View] (2 copies), 1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 43)
  - 5. View from McGown's Pass looking toward Harlem. About 1842., undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 44)
  - 6. William Street at Exchange Place about 1831 (2 copies), 1914 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 44)
  - Announcements about launch of engravings in series, 1911 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 45)
- Series XV: Eight Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith
  - 1. Park, New York, 1827. Drawn from nature by A. J. Davis (3 copies), 1914 (Box Unknown container 473 for instance of 1. Park, New York, 1827. Drawn from nature by A. J. Davis (3 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 2. City Hall and Park Row 1831 (3 copies), undated (Box Unknown container 474 for instance of 2. City Hall and Park Row 1831 (3 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 3. A View of Broadway and Trinity Church in 1799 (3 copies), 1917 (Box Unknown container 475 for instance of 3. A View of Broadway and Trinity Church in 1799 (3 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 4. A View of Wall Street, Trinity Church and the First Presbyterian Church, about 1825 (2 copies), 1917 (Box Unknown container 476 for instance of 4. A View of Wall Street, Trinity Church and the First Presbyterian Church, about 1825 (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 5. A View of St. Paul's Chapel in 1799 (2 copies), 1918 (Box Unknown container 477 for instance of 5. A View of St. Paul's Chapel in 1799 (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 6. New York [The Collect or Fresh Water Pond] (2 copies), 1920 (Box Unknown container 478 for instance of 6. New York [The Collect or Fresh Water Pond] (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 7. New York from Brooklyn Heights 6th August 1778 (2 copies), 1922 (Box Unknown container 479 for instance of 7. New York from Brooklyn Heights 6th August 1778 (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 8. View of the Opening of our Batteries at Hell Gate... from a Wash Drawing by Archibald Robertson (2 copies), 1926 (Box Unknown container 480 for instance of 8. View of the Opening of our Batteries at Hell Gate... from a Wash Drawing by Archibald Robertson (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - Announcements about publications of Nos. 4 and 6, 1919-1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 46)
- Series XVI: Two Engravings Printed in Colors by Charles Furth
  - 1. City Hall [The Wall-Hill View reengraved by Sidney L. Smith] (2 copies), 1919 (Box Unknown container 481 for instance of 1. City Hall [The Wall-Hill View reengraved by Sidney L. Smith] (2 copies), Folder unknown container)
  - 2. New York. Engraved by Walter M. Aikman, 1921 (Box Unknown container 482 for instance of 2. New York. Engraved by Walter M. Aikman, Folder unknown container)
  - Announcement about publications of No. 2, 1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 47)
- Oversize Prints
  - From Series VIII. Twelve Lithographs by Joseph Pennell
    - 1. Battery Park, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 2. Broadway from Bowling Green, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 3. "Broadway Towers", [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 4. The Stock Exchange, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 5. Nassau Street, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 6. Pine Street, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 7. William Street, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 8. "Building the Building", [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 9. "The Flat Iron", [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 10. Union Square, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 11. Broadway above 23rd Street, [1905] (Folder 1)
    - 12. The Times Building, [1905] (Folder 1)
  - From Series XII. One Mezzotint by S. Arlent Edwards
    - 1. Alexander Hamilton, 1909 (Folder 1)
  - From Series XV. Eight Engravings by W. M. Aikman and Sidney L. Smith
    - 1. Park, New York, 1827. Drawn from nature by A. J. Davis (3 copies), 1914 (Folder 1)
    - 2. City Hall and Park Row 1831 (3 copies), undated (Folder 1)
    - 3. A View of Broadway and Trinity Church in 1799 (3 copies), 1917 (Folder 1)
    - 4. A View of Wall Street, Trinity Church and the First Presbyterian Church, about 1825 (2 copies), 1917 (Folder 1)
    - 5. A View of St. Paul's Chapel in 1799 (2 copies), 1918 (Folder 1)
    - 6. New York [The Collect or Fresh Water Pond] (2 copies), 1920 (Folder 1)
    - 7. New York from Brooklyn Heights 6th August 1778 (2 copies), 1922 (Folder 1)
    - 8. View of the Opening of our Batteries at Hell Gate... from a Wash Drawing by Archibald Robertson (2 copies), 1926 (Folder 1)
  - From Series XVI. Two Engravings Printed in Colors by Charles Furth
    - 1. City Hall [The Wall-Hill View reengraved by Sidney L. Smith] (2 copies), 1919 (Folder 1)
    - 2. New York. Engraved by Walter M. Aikman, 1921 (Folder 1)